A Finding Aid to the Giovanni Martino and Martino Family Papers, 1913-2022, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Giovanni Martino and Martino family papers
1913-2022
Archives of American Art
Martino, Giovanni, 1908-1998
AAA.martgiov
Archival Resource Key
2.5 Linear feet
The papers of Giovanni Martino and Martino family measure 2.5 linear feet and date from 1913 to 2022. Giovanni Martino's career as a painter, and to a lesser extent, his work with his brothers at Martino Studios, is documented though biographical material, correspondence, printed material, photographs, artwork, and one scrapbook. Also found are papers documenting the painting careers of his wife, Eva, and daughters, Nina and Babette.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Giovanni Martino Papers, 1913-2010 (Boxes 1-2, 4; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 2: Eva Martino Papers, circa 1930s-2013 (Box 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Nina Martino Papers, 1942-2022 (Box 2; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Babette Martino Papers, 1945-2013 (Boxes 2-3; 0.4 linear feet)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 2005 by Eva, Nina and Babette Martino, Giovanni Martino's wife and daughters and in 2014 and 2022 by Nina F. Martino.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Biographical / Historical
Giovanni Martino (1908-1998) was a painter in Blue Bell, Pennsylvania. Martino and his six brothers formed Martino Studios in Philadelphia, where Giovanni worked as a graphic artist. Martino's wife, Eva (1916-2012), and daughters Babette (1945-2011) and Nina F. (1942- ) are also artists. Martino studied at the Philadelphia Graphic Sketch Club, Le France Art Institute, Spring Garden Institute, and Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts. He specialized in urban landscape painting and regularly exhibited his work in solo and group exhibitions. In the 1960s, the family moved from Philadelphia to a house in Blue Bell, where each member could have their own painting studio.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Giovanni Martino and Martino family measure 2.5 linear feet and date from 1913 to 2022. Giovanni Martino's career as a painter, and to a lesser extent, his work with his brothers at Martino Studios, is documented though biographical material, correspondence, printed material, photographs, artwork, and one scrapbook. Also found are papers documenting the painting careers of his wife, Eva, and daughters, Nina and Babette.
Scrapbooks; Painters -- Pennsylvania; Drawings; Martino, Ernest; Martino, Eva Marinelli; Martino, Frank; Martino, Nina F.; Martino, William; Martino, Edmond; Martino, Babette; Martino, Antonio; Martino, Albert
- Giovanni Martino Papers, 1944-2001; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 4
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as 6 subseries.
  Missing Title
  1.1: Biographical Material, 1944-2001
  1.2: Correspondence, 1942-1983
  1.3: Printed Material, 1930s-2010
  1.4: Photographs, 1915-1990s
  1.5: Artwork, 1913-1980s
  1.6: Scrapbook, 1933-1959
  Scope and Contents
  Giovanni Martino's papers include scattered biographical material, such as awards and curriculum vitae; a small amount of correspondence documenting awards, sales, and exhibition of his artwork; and exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and other printed material documenting his career and the activities of the Martino family. Photographs include portraits of Martino as well as family photographs of Martino as a child, with his brothers, and with his wife and children. A few photographs depict Martino painting outdoors. Also found are figure and landscape drawings on paper by Martino. Some of his early drawings are signed with the alias "M. Giovanni." One scrapbook contains letters, news clippings, exhibition publications, and photographs.
  - Biographical Material, 1944-2001; 1.1; Archival Resource Key
    - Award Certificates, 1952-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Oversize material housed in box 4, folder 1
    - Biographical Material, 1950s-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Oversize Award Certificates from Box 1, Folder 1, 1944-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1983; 1.2; Archival Resource Key
    - Correspondence, 1942-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material, 1930s-2010; 1.3; Archival Resource Key
    - Book, The Martinos: A Legacy of Art by James McClelland, 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Exhibition and Event Announcements, 1955-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1937; 1940-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7-17)
    - Magazines and Bulletins, 1938-1947; 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
    - News Clippings, circa 1930s-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21-27)
      Oversize material housed in box 4, folder 2
    - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1950s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Oversize News Clippings, 1955-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1915-1990s; 1.4; Archival Resource Key
    - Giovanni Martino and Others, 1915-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29-35)
      Oversize material housed in box 4, folder 3
    - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      Oversize material housed in box 4, folder 4
    - Oversize Photographs of Giovanni Martino and Others from Box 1, Folders 29-35, 1928-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Oversize Photographs of Artwork from Box 2, Folders 1-4, 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Artwork, 1913-1980s; 1.5; Archival Resource Key
    - Artwork, 1913-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Oversized material housed in box 4, folder 5
    - Oversized Artwork from Box 2, Folder 5, circa 1920s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1933-1959; 1.6; Archival Resource Key
    - Scrapbook, 1933-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Eva Martino Papers, circa 1930s-2013; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Eva Martino's papers consist of awards, exhibition publications, and many news clippings documenting her career as a painter. Many of these publications are for group exhibitions with her husband and daughters. Also found are a few original ink drawings by Eva, personal photographs of her and her family, and few letters documenting her professional activities.
  - Award Certificates and Prize Lists, 1965-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Drawings, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1971-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1955-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters, circa 1992-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - News Clippings, 1953-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, circa 1930s-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, circa 1980s-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Nina Martino Papers, 1942-2022; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2
  Nina Martino's papers include documentation on exhibitions, including a retrospective of her work entitled "Illumined Solitude," special events, records of her work as a student at Temple University, and awards. Also found are childhood drawings and ink drawings of figures and animals, as well as watercolor and ink illustrations. Photographs depict Nina as a child, with her family, and her artwork.
  - Awards, 1963-2018; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Certificates and Diplomas, 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Biographical Information, 1942; 2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Book, Illumined Solitude: A Retrospective of Paintings 1980-2007, 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Drawings, circa 1953-1957; circa 1970s-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Sketches, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, circa 1971-2022; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Festival Programs, 1995-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - High School Graduation, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Illustrations, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Letters, 1988-2018; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Masters Thesis, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - News Clippings, 1955-2018; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts Benefit Auction, 2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Photographs, circa 1944-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Poetry, circa 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Scrapbook Pages, 1968-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Temple University Records, 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Donation of Works, 2005, 2015-2019; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Babette Martino Papers, 1945-2013; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Found here are the papers documenting Babette Martino's career as a painter, including awards, professional correspondence, fellowship records, exhibition catalogs, publications, and a portfolio containing images of her work. Additionally, her papers include a few personal items such as her baby book and photographs depicting Babette as a child, with family, and at events.
  - Awards, 1957-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Baby Book, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1969-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Magazines, 2007; 2005; 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Pew Fellowship, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1950s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Printed Material, 1971-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Professional Portfolio, 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook Pages, 1966-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)